vtac.edu.au 2017-06-06

# VTAC Website Privacy Statement - VTAC

The Victorian Tertiary Admissions Centre (VTAC) values the privacy of every individual's personal information and we are committed to handling your personal information consistent with our obligations under the _Australian Privacy Principles (March 2014)_.

This Privacy Policy sets out how and what information is collected, maintained and disclosed (including identification of individuals) for the services VTAC provides. VTAC is the central office that administers the application processes for places in tertiary courses, scholarships and Special Entry Access Schemes (SEAS) at universities, TAFE institutes and private tertiary colleges in Victoria and a few outside Victoria.

If you do not agree to any of the provisions of this Policy, you should not use VTAC’s website or services, lodge a VTAC application or provide VTAC with any personal information.

By visiting the VTAC website, submitting an application for a course, scholarship or SEAS, registering for a tertiary admission test, using any of our services or providing us with your information, you agree to the information being collected, held, used and disclosed as set out in this Privacy Policy.

## Application of the Privacy Policy

This privacy statement applies to all methods of collecting personal information (including hardcopy, electronic or verbal means) including but not limited to the following: 

  * online VTAC applications and services 
  * variation to personal details 
  * receipt of educational results 
  * calculation of the ATAR, if necessary 
  * additional documentation provided by you as part of your application(s) 
  * electronic information provided as part of your application(s) 
  * surveys you may complete 
  * digital images captured for applicant identification purposes
  * exam and tertiary studies results from relevant institutions. 

If you would like further information about or clarification of the information handling practices at VTAC or require more detail than this document provides, please contact the Privacy Officer at:

**Privacy Officer**  
VTAC  
40 Park Street   
South Melbourne VIC 3205 

Telephone: +61 1300 364 133  
Email: [privacy@vtac.edu.au](mailto:privacy@vtac.edu.au)

## What is information collected for? 

Information is collected by us for the primary purposes of:

  * calculating the ATAR (Australian Tertiary Admission Rank) for Year 12 VCE and International Baccalaureate (IB) students
  * processing and assessing applications for admission to tertiary courses on behalf of VTAC’s participating institutions. This includes providing institutions with information to support one or more of the following so that selection authorities may advise you accordingly of your success or otherwise: 
    * Booking for tertiary admission tests 
    * Course application 
    * Application for consideration under Special Entry Access Schemes (SEAS) 
    * Application for scholarships 

VTAC also collects personal information as required to meet the reporting requirements of the Departments of Education and Training (DET) and Industry, Innovation and Science (DIIS) or their successors.

### How personal information is collected 

We obtain personal information in a number of ways including:

  * directly from you when you submit an application or respond to requests for information;
  * each time we have contact with you (email, telephone, written correspondence, in person, private message via Facebook); 
  * from third parties, such as:
    * your school 
    * the Victorian Curriculum and Assessment Authority and interstate admission centres providing Year 12 results
    * the International Baccalaureate Organisation (IBO) 
    * the New Zealand Qualifications Authority (NZQA) and Cambridge International Examinations (CIE) 
    * Australian Council for Educational Research (ACER) 
    * tertiary institutions that hold results relevant to your application 
    * Centrelink
    * other persons or agencies you have authorised to act as your referees or to supply personal information on your behalf 

In providing the details of your authorised person or agency to VTAC you are consenting to the collection of your personal information from your authorised person or agency.

Generally, you will be aware we have collected personal information or have authorised collection of personal information from third parties or be aware that we are obtaining information from them.

## Unsolicited personal information

If we receive unsolicited personal information, as soon as reasonably possible we determine if we could have collected the personal information under the Australian Privacy Principles (APP).

If we consider we could have collected the personal information, we will retain it as if we had collected it under the APP.

If we consider we could not have collected the personal information, we will (if it is lawful and reasonable to do so) destroy the information or ensure the information is de-identified.

## What personal information is collected?

### VTAC account creation 

The personal information that is required to create an account with VTAC includes: 

  * citizenship /residency status
  * full name, including any previous names
  * address(es) including mailing and permanent residence
  * email address
  * telephone number(s)
  * date of birth 
  * gender
  * language spoken at home
  * country of birth
  * year of arrival in Australia if relevant
  * whether or not you are currently studying specific senior secondary programs

This information is not used until a subsequent VTAC application or booking is submitted. 

## VTAC course application

The personal information that is required to lodge a VTAC course application includes: 

  * information provided in the creation of your account
  * processing payments you have authorised
  * secondary and tertiary qualifications attempted or completed
  * current and previous educational results including: 
    * Victorian Certificate of Education (VCE) or its interstate equivalent, Victorian Certificate of Applied Language (VCAL) or the International Baccalaureate (IB) in Australia
    * the New Zealand Qualifications Authority (NZQA) and Cambridge International Examinations 
    * Australian higher education results 
    * special tertiary admissions test results 
    * other examination results 
  * your course preferences 

For some courses, you may be requested to complete a VTAC Personal Statement to support your application. This can include the following information: 

  * motivation for undertaking courses on your preference list
  * work and community experience
  * proficiency in other languages

VTAC also collects information as required by the government, which includes

  * number and gender of parent(s)/guardian(s)
  * qualifications of parent(s)/guardian(s), which may include their highest education level. 

This information is not used as part of the selection process but for the collection of governmental statistics.

You also have the option of providing other personal information including whether or not you have a disability. Your response is not part of the selection process, but rather to ensure that you have adequate access to support services provided by the institution in which you enrol.

VTAC automatically seeks to collect the following information to process your application:

  * current or previous results for secondary school studies or equivalent for all applicants from the relevant issuing/reporting authorities
  * claimed previous STAT or ALSET results from the relevant issuing/reporting authority
  * results for claimed tertiary studies from the relevant tertiary institutions

## VTAC Special Entry Access Scheme (SEAS) application

If you are submitting a SEAS application, you may be requested to provide or authorise VTAC for the collection of the following personal information:

  * information provided in the creation of your account 
  * sensitive information about your personal circumstances
  * health information
  * financial information

You may be asked to provide the personal details of another person (for example Centrelink documents for your parent or guardian). By providing this information you are agreeing that you have provided it with the consent of that person, and that they know about this Privacy Policy and where to find it. 

## VTAC Scholarships application

If you are submitting a scholarship application, you may be requested to provide or authorise VTAC to collect on your behalf the following personal information:

  * information provided in the creation of your account
  * sensitive information about your personal circumstances
  * health information
  * financial information

You may be asked to provide the personal details of another person (for example Centrelink or tax documents for your parent or guardian). By providing this information you are agreeing that you have provided it with the consent of that person, and that they know about this Privacy Policy and where to find it.

## How we use your information

VTAC only uses your personal information for the purpose for which it was provided to us, other directly related purposes or purposes for which you otherwise consent, and as otherwise required or permitted by law.

Such purposes include:

  * confirming the data contained within your application(s)
  * confirming academic results
  * the calculation of an Australian Tertiary Admission Rank (ATAR) for eligible VCE students and a notional ATAR for Victorian IB students
  * the calculation of a Grade Point Average (GPA) for university results which VTAC has been able to access electronically via the Automated Results Transfer Scheme (ARTS)
  * maintaining/processing/assessing your application(s)
  * provision of any information about VTAC’s services that may be relevant to you
  * notifying you of missing information, deadlines, course requirements, cancelled courses, change of preferences and offers
  * to identify you when you log into VTAC’s online services or otherwise contact VTAC
  * responding to your enquiries
  * assessing your eligibility for courses
  * to meet reporting requirements of the Departments of  Education and Training (DET) and Industry, Innovation and Science (DIIS) or their successors
  * for benchmarking, analyses, quality assurance and planning purposes
  * assessing eligibility for the allocation of special consideration through access and equity programs
  * assessing eligibility for the allocation of scholarships
  * our own internal research purposes
  * (in de-identified form) for governmental and educational socio/economic research purposes
  * as required by law. 

## SEAS and scholarships applications 

VTAC only uses your health information in accordance with the Health Information Privacy Act 1998 and _Australian Privacy Principles (March 2014)._  The information collected as part of the SEAS and scholarships applications is used for the purpose for which it was provided to us or purposes for which you otherwise consent, and as otherwise required or permitted by law.

## How we disclose your information

Information collected as part of the creation of your account is held by VTAC and used to identify you for assistance with VTAC services or disclosed as part of a subsequent VTAC service.

All information collected as part of the course application, VTAC personal statement, Special Tertiary Admissions Test and Australian Law Schools Entrance Test, Scholarships and SEAS applications will be distributed to the institutions to which you have applied for courses or have expressly given permission to access and you have paid the VTAC processing fee(s) for that service.

All information collected as part of the SEAS application will be distributed to the institutions to which you have applied for courses to for consideration under their stated access and equity schemes. 

All information collected as part of the Scholarship application will be distributed to the institutions to which you have applied for scholarship(s).

Your information may be disclosed to other third parties as follows:

  * Institutions where you have studied or where VTAC reasonably believes you have studied for the purpose of confirming your results., academic records and offer information. 
  * In the event that you contact a VTAC institution about the status of your application, upon request from that institution,  VTAC will provide confirmation of your identification details including your name, date of birth, gender; your VTAC application status including your category of application; course preference history  and offer information. 
  * VTAC cooperative off-shore entities such as the International Baccalaureate in Wales, Cambridge International Examinations and the New Zealand Qualifications Authority (NZQA), if necessary for the purpose of confirming your enrolment and obtaining your results. These recipients may not provide the level of data protection provided by the APP. While we request these recipients protect your personal information, we cannot be accountable for how these recipients handle your personal information. The creation of your VTAC account by you, constitutes your consent to disclosure to those overseas recipients.
  * Agencies involved in the release of tertiary education results both in Australia and overseas for the purpose of confirming your results, if necessary.
  * Government departments such as the Victorian Curriculum and Assessment Authority or its interstate equivalent, Victorian Electoral Commission, the Department of Education and Early Childhood Development or its successor;
  * Agencies and organisations involved in quality assurance, planning and research for tertiary education such as federal and state government, TEQSA, interstate tertiary admissions centres and Universities Australia.
  * Contracted service providers which VTAC uses to perform services on its behalf (such as mailing houses, logistics and IT service providers).
  * Legal advisers or other professional advisers and consultants engaged by VTAC.
  * Your ATAR may be disclosed to the Victorian Curriculum and Assessment Authority (VCAA) if required for the purpose of awarding the Australian Student Prize. 
  * State or federal law enforcement authorities where required or authorised by law.
  *  (In de-identified form) for governmental and educational socio/economic research purposes.
  * As required by law.

Additionally VTAC will also distribute the following information to your secondary school, via VTAC CourseLink (web based course information and counselling program), for the purpose of counselling and record keeping:

  * whether or not you have created an account with VTAC
  * whether or not you have applied for courses through VTAC
  * your course preferences and payment indicators if you apply
  * your ATAR
  * your offer(s)

You can write to VTAC at any time to have your details removed from the school file, however this may affect your schools’ ability to provide counselling advice to you.

## Security of your information

We have taken reasonable steps to protect your personal information from misuse, interference or loss and from unauthorised access, modification or disclosure.

The information collected by VTAC is maintained on electronic databases, held securely within VTAC and with VTAC’s service provider which resides outside of the VTAC offices. Arrangements with our provider requires personal information we collect to be stored on a server in Australia only and for our providers to comply with the Australian Privacy Principles (APP) with respect to that personal information. We have requested any overseas recipient of information to comply with the APP as if they were an entity bound by them.

Irrespective of whether or not your course application is successful, your information will become part of VTAC archive and will be protected under the relevant privacy legislation. 

Examination or educational results, including the ATAR, held within the VTAC archive will only be accessed by VTAC or any other tertiary admission centre or institution if you initiate an application for courses through that centre or if you submit an application for tertiary study directly with an institution participating through that centre.  

## Data quality and accuracy

We take reasonable steps to ensure that the personal information we collect, issue or disclose is accurate, complete, up to date, and relevant to the purpose for which it was collected and not misleading. The personal information you submit at the time of your application(s) to VTAC is assumed to be accurate, relevant, complete, up to date and relevant to the purpose for which it was collected and not misleading.

Despite the measures we have put in place, the accuracy of your information, particularly in relation to transmission online, may not be guaranteed. You must take care to ensure that your data is accurate, relevant, complete and not misleading and should notify us as soon as possible after you become aware of any discrepancies.

There are circumstances under which we may refuse to correct personal information, but if we do so, we will inform you of the reasons and the mechanisms available to you to complain about the refusal.

## Fraudulent information

VTAC considers the provision of fraudulent information to be serious misconduct in relation to VTAC’s functions. Therefore, if VTAC has reason to suspect that you have presented fraudulent information of any kind, we may use or disclose your personal information in a manner inconsistent with this policy to the extent required to undertake an investigation into the fraudulent information and to take appropriate action in light of the outcome of the investigation.

## Direct Marketing

We will not sell or trade your personal information to any third party for marketing purposes. 

## Access to your personal information

You have a right to access your personal information held by us. There are circumstances where we may refuse to give you access to some of your personal information. For example, we are not required to provide you with access where a request:

  * is frivolous or vexatious;
  * concerns information relating to an existing or anticipated legal proceedings between VTAC and yourself;
  * requires access that would be unlawful;
  * would be likely to prejudice the prevention, investigation and prosecution of any criminal offence or seriously improper conduct. 

If we refuse to give you access, we will give you written notice of the reasons for refusal and the mechanisms available to you to complain about the refusal

## Access to personal information by authorised nominees

An authorised nominee is a person who has been nominated by the VTAC applicant, to manage the administration of the application to which the authorised nominee's name has been assigned in circumstances where the applicant is unable to manage the administration of the application themselves. For details of what an authorised nominee can and cannot access see [Authorised nominee: definition, rights and responsibilities](http://vtac.edu.au/applying/courses/changes/authorised-nominee.html). 

## What to do if you have a complaint concerning privacy

If you wish to make an enquiry or formal complaint about a possible breach of this Privacy Policy you can contact our Privacy Officer.

**Privacy Officer**  
VTAC  
40 Park Street   
South Melbourne VIC 3205 

Telephone: +61 1300 364 133  
Email: [privacy@vtac.edu.au](mailto:privacy@vtac.edu.au)

Normal office hours are Monday to Friday between 9.00 am and 5.00pm Melbourne time. Formal complaints about a breach of this Privacy Policy or the APP must be made in writing to the Privacy Officer. VTAC reserves the right to request any supporting evidence and/or information to substantiate the complaint/breach.

The VTAC Privacy Officer will investigate the issue and determine the steps we will undertake to resolve your complaint. We will contact you if we require any additional information from you and will notify you in writing of the determination in relation to your complaint.

If you are not satisfied with our determination, you can refer the complaint to the Australian Privacy Commissioner via [www.oaic.gov.au](http://www.oaic.gov.au/)

While current and previous Year 12 results are stored on a national database, this information will only be accessed by VTAC or any other tertiary admission centre if you initiate an application for courses through that centre. 

## Google Analytics and "Cookies"

This website uses Google Analytics and Google Tag Manager, web analytics services provided by Google, Inc. ("Google"). Google Analytics and Google Tag Manager use "cookies", which are text files placed on your computer, to help the website analyse how users use the site. The information generated by the cookie about your use of the website (including your IP address) will be transmitted to and stored by Google on servers in the United States. Google will use this information for the purpose of evaluating your use of the website, compiling reports on website activity for website operators and providing other services relating to website activity and internet usage. Google may also transfer this information to third parties where required to do so by law, or where such third parties process the information on Google's behalf. Google will not associate your IP address with any other data held by Google. You may refuse the use of cookies by selecting the appropriate settings on your browser, however please note that if you do this you may not be able to use the full functionality of this website. By using this website, you consent to the processing of data about you by Google in the manner and for the purposes set out above.

### Logged-in user, demographic and interest reporting

VTAC uses a specific cookie in order to facilitate the use of Google Universal Analytics for users logged-in to the VTAC account or applications. If you are logged-in, VTAC may use a unique ID in combination with Google Analytics to track and analyse pages you view and services you use. This unique ID is distinct from your VTAC user ID. VTAC will not upload any data that allows Google to personally identify an individual (such as certain names, social security numbers, email addresses, or any similar data), or data that permanently identifies a particular device (such as a mobile phone’s unique device identifier if such an identifier cannot be reset).    
VTAC has also implemented Demographics and Interest Reporting from the Google Analytics Advertising Features. VTAC will use this data to improve and expand information and services through a better understanding of visitors to our website and how they use our website. Visitors can opt out of Google’s interest-based ads or edit the interests and demographics associated with their Google Account by changing [Ad settings](https://www.google.com/settings/ads). 

Visitors can also block tracking by Google Analytics by installing the [Google Analytics Opt-out Browser Add-on](https://tools.google.com/dlpage/gaoptout/), available for all common browsers.

This feature does not affect this Privacy Policy as it applies to applicants.

**Last updated:** 29 July 2016
